<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[John Eastman]]></title>
  <link href="http://jeastman.info/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jeastman.info/"/>
  <updated>2012-12-28T07:44:40-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://jeastman.info/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[John Eastman]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[CDMI]]></title>
    <link href="http://jeastman.info/blog/2012/12/17/cdmi/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-17T08:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jeastman.info/blog/2012/12/17/cdmi</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Storage Networking Industry Association (<a href="http://snia.org">SNIA</a>) has
produced a specification called <a href="http://snia.org/cdmi">CDMI</a> (Cloud Data
Management Interface). CDMI provides an
<a href="http://cdmi.sniacloud.org">interface specification</a> for accessing and
managing data in the Cloud. The CDMI specification was recently designated
an International Standard by the Joint Technical Committee 1 (JCT 1), a
joint effort of the
<a href="http://www.iso.org/iso/home.html">International Organization for Standardization</a>
(ISO) and the
<a href="http://www.iec.ch/">International Electrotechnical Commission</a> (IEC).</p>

<p>The standard designation by ISO has stirred up a considerable amount of
interest in CDMI. I also have a lot of interest in this specification and
it is a topic I will likely touch on in future posts, so I thought I would
cover some background information.</p>

<p>Cloud storage, in general, has seen a lot of press recently. Most of the
interest appears to be around the consumer based offerings for personal
online storage. These isolated services fill the need for individuals, but
offer very little in terms of interoperability and portability. Several
services provide APIs or developer SDKs, but they are very proprietary. The
more services you integrate into them and the more storage you use, the
harder it becomes to move off of them. If these online storage services
were to adopt a standard interface, it might be easier to migrate between
them from a service integration perspective. However, moving large amounts
of storage from one vendor to another would continue to be an issue.</p>

<p>CDMI attempts to address the first part of the problem, providing a
standard interface. The surface benefits of this to both the end user and
application vendor are easy to see. Vendors producing client applications
could simply write their application to the standard and provide support
for any service supporting the standard. End users could happily use their
chosen applications on the service of their choice. While CDMI provides a
mechanism for serializing data into and out of a particular vendor&#8217;s
storage service implementation, physics of bandwidth and data size get in
the way of this being practical.</p>

<p>There are a couple of features of CDMI that I particularly like:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Capabilities</p>

<p> CDMI defines a capabilities model that allows client applications to
 discover the capabilities of particular service. This gives client
 applications the ability to determine if a particular service has the
 features they require. The capabilities defined in the specification
 cover all aspects of the service, including service levels. This
 includes security features, throughput requirements as well as being
 able to define higher level features like Restore Point and Restore
 Time Objectives (RPO/RTO). The specification also provides a means for
 the service to report back to the client actual values that the service
 is able to achieve for these features. Having features like this
 provides a programmatic means for client applications to actually
 inspect the service level delivered.</p></li>
<li><p>Metadata</p>

<p> Client applications can store metadata as part of any object in
 CDMI. While this is not unique, the metadata can actually have an
 effect on an object. Most capabilities supported by the service have
 corresponding metadata values that can be used to trigger or modify the
 capability.</p></li>
<li><p>Management</p>

<p> CDMI provides a means of actually managing your data, not just storing
 and retrieving it. The specification has a concept of containers, that
 may be nested, acting like folders of a file system. Metadata can be
 placed on containers and inherited by the objects it contains.</p></li>
<li><p>Non-CDMI access</p>

<p> It does not always make sense to access data stored in a service
 through the CDMI interface. If a particular client (a web browser for
 example) does not know how to construct nor interpret a CDMI request,
 it should still be able to gain access to the content. The CDMI
 specification actually covers these cases, thereby standardizing how
 all clients access a service. This also allows one to use a CDMI
 enabled service as something like a web server.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>The CDMI specification provides not only the basic requirements for a Cloud
Storage Service, but it also includes features that provide higher level
control over the stored data. These features allow for client applications
that go beyond simple file storage and enables them to support the
requirements of real businesses. While there is not anything that can
combat the physics of infrastructure, a standard interface for data
portability addresses a large set of the issues.</p>

<p>If you have not looked at the specification itself, head over to
<a href="http://cdmi.sniacloud.org">cdmi.sniacloud.org</a> to check it out. The &#8220;Overview of Cloud Storage&#8221; (Section 5) is well worth the read. Another good source of information on CDMI is the <a href="http://blogs.netapp.com/context/">Objects in Context</a>
blog which aggregates a number of CDMI sources from around the internet as
well as providing original content.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Every blog has its first post...]]></title>
    <link href="http://jeastman.info/blog/2012/12/10/first-post/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-10T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jeastman.info/blog/2012/12/10/first-post</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hello, and welcome to my blog!</p>

<p>Everything has to start somewhere, and this blog starts here. I find that I
gather a lot of little bits and pieces of things that I tend to share with
people individually. I&#8217;ll be posting these things here to serve as a
reference and hopefully help some other people along the way. Expect to see
primarily articles about technology, personal optimization, and maybe some
code here and there.</p>

<p>I hope you&#8217;ll enjoy reading the things you find here.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
